Good afternoon
大家好
我是 Thiago Komeno
Today, my talk is going to be on How to win the Swift Student Challenge
So let's get start it
First of all, I'd like to thank my friend YC
for introducing me the opportunity to be speaking today in Taiwan
So, thank you so much
He's not present here today
I think he's in America right now
But thank you so much YC
And now a little bit about myself
My name is Thiago Komeno
Thiago is my first name
It's Portuguese
Komeno is my last name
It's Japanese
In Chinese, it would be 米野雅各
And I am Japanese-Brazilian
Currently, I live in Tokyo
I'm a university student over there
I've been studying Mandarin Chinese for four to five years already
Traditional Chinese
I really like Zhuyin
Last year, I came to Taiwan
I bought this postcard
I was learning Zhuyin at that time
Now I already can type on my phone
But on my computer, unfortunately, I use Pinyin
Sorry
So, a little bit about my process on how did I get into coding
I learned to program in this school
It's a French coding school called École 42
And last year, I was also a Google Student Ambassador at Google Japan
And early this year, I was an iOS developer intern at MIXI Inc.
It's a Japanese company in Shibuya
And currently, I'm a full-stack developer at a startup called BaseMe Inc.
Also in Shibuya, Japan
And from next month, I'll be going to this company called Sansan Inc.
Also as an iOS developer intern
And also LINE Yahoo! (LY Corporation) in Fukuoka, Japan
This is from next month
I didn't begin yet
I'm excited for those opportunities
In Japan, I usually attend to a lot of community events for Swift students
And one of those events that I attended last year
I got to know about the Swift Student Challenge through one of those events
And I decided to participate because I always wanted to build my own apps
And, like, personally, I like personal development (indie development)
And that sounded like a good opportunity to get into
as a motivation to get into those apps and developing those apps
So, yeah
Now, just briefly about what is the Swift Student Challenge
This is the main topic for today
So, the Swift Student Challenge is an annual coding competition hosted by Apple for students
The challenge encourages students to showcase their coding skills by creating an interactive and creative Swift playground project
So, if you never heard about the Swift Student Challenge, you might be thinking
oh, maybe I can build a social media app or like a live streaming app or even like a music player app
But there are some important constraints we have to mind
First of all, the app has to be submitted in a zip file, and the file can't be over 25 MB
Second, the whole core experience of the app has to be done in under three minutes
And third, the whole app experience, the whole playground has to be completely offline
So, with those constraints in mind, I submitted my first app in 2025
Last year, it was called NeoMnemo
This app, the idea behind this app was really simple
So, you would just type a keyword you wanted to memorize
and then you would, like, imagine a story in your mind to help you memorize that keyword
And I used the image playground API to generate an image based on the concept you wanted to memorize
So, this was basically a flashcards app that would help you memorize some abstract or hard-to-memorize concepts
And, yeah, that idea was based on my personal story
When I was going to enter university in Japan, I had to study Japanese history
And that was really hard for me because I grew up in Brazil
My whole life I spent in Brazil
So, studying Japanese history was really hard, especially to memorize like people's name, event's name and dates
So, I decided to create short stories to kind of like help me memorize those concepts in Japanese history
And this method was really effective because in the entrance exam for my university in Japan
I scored like 98 out of 100
So, this was a pretty good methodology that I used to study Japanese history
But unfortunately, my app NeoMnemo ended up not winning last year
And those are some of the reasons why I think my app didn't win
The first one
So, as you guys just saw the app was kind of like a good tool to use
But yeah, it was just a tool
It wasn't like some kind of experience that people could like get to know more about myself, my personal story
or like who I am
So, this was the first reason why I think I didn't get to win last year
And the second one was that even though the concept that inspired me to make this app was based on a personal story
that didn't reflect in the app's design and implementation and interactions
So, those are the reasons why I think I didn't win last year
This year, I decided to try once again to participate into the challenge for my second time with my app called Diary
And, basically, the inspiration behind this app was that last year I went back to my hometown, São Paulo in Brazil
And when I was in my home. My dad, he came to me and he was holding, like three diaries from my grandfather
And he asked me, Can you read those diaries? They're all in Japanese
Maybe you can read them
And then I looked at the diaries. I can speak Japanese, modern Japanese
but those diaries, they were written in old Japanese
So, the Japanese language passed through a language reform in the 50s
and all the characters in Japanese changed
So, they became kind of like simplified
And that gave me an idea to make an app
So, I wanted to combine all those elements
my personal story, language learning, and history of Japanese immigration to Brazil
So, with all those concepts in mind
I decided to create an experience to help Japanese Brazilians rediscover their roots
And while doing that, they would also learn the history of how the Japanese language changed in those 100 years
So, I decided to make an initial prototype for this app, and it looked like this
First, the data I used for the initial prototype
I decided to look for a conversion table between kyūjitai and shinjitai
In Chinese, it would be something like the traditional Chinese and simplified Chinese
And I just looked it up on GitHub and found this JSON table in a repository called Kyujipy
And yeah, I decided to build a really simple prototype for my first initial version of my app
It was basically a phrase in Japanese would appear containing the old character over there
And users would read the phrase, look for the corresponding character in modern Japanese, and select the answer
And I even tried to add difficulty to my app
so characters with similar radicals or similar components would appear in the hard version of the app
But there was a problem
This app was still not a whole experience
It felt more like a test or an exam or a learning tool
And it wasn't like an immersive experience yet
So yeah, from that point on, I decided to convert this game,
This kind of like test like experience into an immersive experience, an immersive game
So, I started by building my onboarding screen, and it looked like this
I first introduced my background, who I am
I'm Japanese-Brazilian
And then one day, I decided to go into my family's basement
And in the basement, when you enter, there are some objects up here
And users have to use their fingers to move the objects around and review the diary behind it
And for giving kind of like a mysterious look to the diary, I decided to use a shader, a metal shader
I used Paul Hudson's Inferno to add this effect
And also, I don't know if you guys know this game
I really like it. It's one of my favorite games
It's called Chrono Trigger
And I decided to add kind of like an effect for the time-traveling experience when you enter the diary and go to the past
So, this is just one of my inspirations for creating this theme
And once you get into the diary
you can start reading the entries that my grandfather wrote
and like review the modern versions of all the old Japanese characters that appears in the sentence
So, the app now felt more like this
You would see the old form and the modern form of the characters
And also, at the same time, you would be learning the history of Japanese immigration to Brazil
because all the entries are based on real entries
And how I did that was by actually going outside visiting museums
and also reading a lot of documents based on Japanese immigration
So, one of the places I visited was the Yokohama Japanese Overseas Migration Museum
It's in Yokohama
And I read lots of documents
So, you guys can see some of the images of the museum right here
I read some of those books to get to know more about Japanese immigration
And the final experience looked like this
So, a phrase in old Japanese based on those documents would appear
Users would tap the phrase
And in the top, I inserted a panel that would automatically scroll
and review the modern versions of the characters in Japanese
So, that's how the whole experience looks like
When you finish, there is an English translation that appears in the panel
And I also added a glowing effect to the panel when you finish all the characters in a certain page
So, that's the comparison between the initial prototype that I made in the beginning
and the final experience
So yeah, by creating this app
I could combine all of the elements I wanted to combine
my personal roots, my story, immigration, Japanese immigration history
and also language learning
So, the final experience looked like this
And with that app
I won the Swift Student Challenge this year and received the certificate
Thank you so much
And finally, I'd like to close this talk by telling you guys some of the things that I learned
by trying the challenge this year
And if some of you are thinking about joining the challenge, just do it
Because this year I was going to do an internship at a company
so I wasn't thinking about joining the challenge, even though I'm a student
Because last year I didn't win, and I was kind of not motivated to join
But then I decided to visit some community events in Japan
and this was one of the best experiences in my life
because it was a great experience to learn more about myself
to build an actual meaningful application
And also, if you guys are thinking about building something for your community
for your family members or even for yourself
just do it because you will learn a lot about yourself
You might help a family member or even someone from your community
So, I'd like to close with this phrase
Sometimes the best idea is not always the biggest idea
Sometimes the best idea is the one that only you could have made
So, thank you so much for listening
And those are my socials
If you guys want to scan and follow me on any of the social media platforms
feel free to do so
Thank you so much